The sands will rise. The heavens will part. The power will be unleashed.
The Mummy is a adventure, action, fantasy film directed by Stephen Sommers.
Dashing legionnaire Rick O'Connell stumbles upon the hidden ruins of Hamunaptra
while in the midst of a battle to claim the area in 1920s Egypt.
It has been over three thousand years since former High Priest Imhotep suffered a fate worse than death as a punishment
for a forbidden love—along with a curse that guarantees eternal doom upon the world if he is ever awoken.
Rick O'Connell, played by Brendan Fraser.
Evelyn Carnahan, played by Rachel Weisz.
Jonathan Carnahan, played by John Hannah.
Imhotep, played by Arnold Vosloo.
Anck-Su-Namun, played by Patricia Velásquez.
Ardeth Bay, played by Oded Fehr.
The Mummy is a 1999 American action-adventure film written and directed by Stephen Sommers, starring
Brendan Fraser, Rachel Weisz, John Hannah, and Arnold Vosloo as the reanimated mummy.
It is a loose remake of the 1932 film.
The Mummy follows adventurer and treasure hunter Rick O'Connell as he travels to Hamunaptra, the City of the Dead, with librarian Evelyn
Carnahan and her older brother Jonathan, where they accidentally awaken Imhotep, a cursed high priest with supernatural powers.
Development took years, with multiple screenplays and directors attached.
In 1997, Sommers successfully pitched his version of a more
adventurous and romantic take on the source material.
Filming took place in Morocco and the United Kingdom; the crew endured dehydration,
sandstorms, and snakes shooting on location in the Sahara Desert.
Industrial Light & Magic provided many of the visual effects, blending live-action
footage and computer-generated imagery to create the titular monster.
Jerry Goldsmith composed the orchestral score.
The Mummy was theatrically released on May 7, 1999, by Universal Pictures.
The film received mixed critical reviews but grossed $422.5 million worldwide against a
production budget of $80 million, becoming the sixth-highest-grossing film of 1999.
The film started a new franchise, with two direct sequels, The Mummy Returns in 2001 and The Mummy: Tomb of the Dragon Emperor in 2008, and various
spinoffs such as an animated series which ran from 2001 to 2003, and the prequel The Scorpion King in 2002, which led to sequels of its own.
In 2017, an attempt was made to start another Universal Monsters
franchise with The Mummy starring Tom Cruise.
In November 2025, a new sequel featuring Fraser and Weisz was announced, to be directed
by Matt Bettinelli-Olpin and Tyler Gillett of Radio Silence Productions.
The film explores themes of egypt, cairo, library, secret passage, pastor.
The tone is lighthearted and intense.